<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE dynamideDoco>
<dynamideDoco pageTitle='Security'>
<!--
<topic id="security">
   <indices>
     <name>security</name>
   </indices>
</topic>
-->
<!-- or, just allow inline tags, and then scan for them: -->

<indexTarget id="security overview"/>
<h4>
The following security features are implemented in Dynamide.
</h4>

<P>
The DynamideServlet installs its own SecurityManager.
This SecurityManager disallows dangerous activity, from the viewpoint of the owner of the application server in which Dynamide runs.
</P>

<P>
Specifically, these activities have been disallowed:
</P>

        <UL>
            <LI>System Exit</LI>
            <LI>Exec</LI>
            <LI>Socket Listen (server sockets)</LI>
            <LI>File Access  </LI>
        </UL>

<P>
All Dynamide applications run within a DynamideWorkerThreadGroup threadgroup.   You are allowed to spin off threads,
but they will still have DynamideWorkerThreadGroup in their parent chain.  Code in a DynamideWorkerThreadGroup
does not have the same permissions as the DynamideResourceManager,
so to access protected resources, you should use the DynamideResourceManager.
</P>

<hr />

<h2>Security Implementation</h2>

<P>
There is a master list of permissions:
<pre>
file
    open
    read
    write
process
    run
application
    create_user
    create_account
    create_assembly
Page, Widget, Application
    read
    write



</pre>

(There must be some way to secure each of the actions above.  So create_assembly must
be blocked by the thing that saves files, and delegated to an object that CAN create assemblies.
This is because assemblies are just files, but creating them as files allows
a set of permissions the next time assemblies are re-read.

A process acquires these permissions when run as a user.
Objects require the permissions.  The ResourceManager checks that the process
contains required permissions when accessing an object of a given type.
For example, if Page requires read permission, the process must contain
page.read permission.
</P>


</dynamideDoco>